Guide to the Joyce Gibson Roach Papers
The Wittliff Collections
Joyce Gibson Roach Papers
1950-1991
1970-1980
The Wittliff Collections https://www.thewittliffcollections.txstate.edu
Roach, Joyce Gibson
SWWC.003
4 Linear Feet
8 boxes
The Joyce Gibson Roach papers date from 1961 to 1991 with the bulk of the material dating from 1970 to 1980. The collection contains the notes, clippings, interviews, articles, brochures, cassettes, and letters used by Roach in the writing of The Cowgirls and C. L. Sonnichsen: Folk Historian.
Scope and Contents
The Joyce Gibson Roach papers date from 1961 to 1991 with the bulk of the material dating from 1970 to 1980. The collection contains the notes, clippings, interviews, articles, brochures, cassettes, and letters used by Roach in the writing of The Cowgirls and C. L. Sonnichsen: Folk Historian. There are two series representing the above mentioned works.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Joyce Gibson Roach, 1991-1994.
Biographical Notes
Joyce Gibson Roach was born December 18, 1935 in Jacksboro, Texas. She received a BFA in 1958 and an MA in 1964 from Texas Christian University.
Having lived all her life in ranch country, Roach has had a lifelong interest in western folklore. She is active in the Texas Folklore Society of which she was president in 1976. She has contributed articles to magazines such as Western Folklore, Horseman, and Southwest Heritage. She received the Spur Award from Western Writers of America in 1977 for The Cowgirls.
Related Materials
University of Texas-Arlington has 2 linear feet of Roach's materials.
Index Terms
Subjects
Folklorists -- Texas; Women authors, Texan; Cowgirls -- History
Subjects (Persons)
Roach, Joyce Gibson; Sonnichsen, C. L. (Charles Leland), 1901-1991
- The Cowgirls, 1961-1977
  Series Description
  In The Cowgirls, Roach examines the role of women in the forming of the West. The book considers women as ranchers, pistol packers, and rodeo stars. Women in western society and culture are further investigated through a look at movies, songs, dime novels and humor. This series contains answers to Roach's research queries, notes, articles, brochures, clippings, cassettes, letters, photographs and interviews. It is organized generally in the chapter order of the finished book.
  - Responses to research queries, 1969-1977 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
  - Articles on cowgirls, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Outline (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Drafts, various chapters (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Who Were Cowgirls" (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Horsewomen" (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Indian Women" (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Farm vs. Ranch" (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Frontier Women" (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "How Horse Women Tamed the West" (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "Indian Menace" (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - "Women in Men's Clothes" (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "Women Generally" (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
  - "Heroines Generally" (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "Reputation" (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "Suffrage" (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - First Chapter (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - First Chapter, Title, Dedication, Index (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Acknowledgments (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Introduction (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
  - "Up the Trail" (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - "Women on the Trail" (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - "Backwood Belles" (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Lizzie Johnson (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - "Lady Ranchers" (Box 2, Folder 19, Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - "Lay That Pistol Down, Babe" (Box 3, Folder 3-5)
  - Sally Skull (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
  - Cattle Kate (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Alice Stillwell Henderson (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - "Lady Rustlers" (Box 3, Folder 10-12)
  - Cattle Wars (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Lucille Marshall (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Ruth Roach (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - "Out of the Chutes" (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Rodeo (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Rodeo - Tad Lucas (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Rodeo - Mabel Woodward (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - 20 Rodeo - Don Russell (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Rodeo (three audiocassettes in folder 4) (Box 4, Folder 1-6)
  - Cowgirl in the Movies (Box 4, Folder 7-10, Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Clothes (Box 5, Folder 2-4)
  - Cowgirls in Literature (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Ranch Romance Novels (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Dime Novels (Box 5, Folder 7-10)
  - Verse and Song (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Humor (Box 6, Folder 2-4)
  - Last Chapter: She's Mounted and Gone (photographs in folder 6) (Box 6, Folder 5-6)
  - Manuscript rejections (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Final drafts (Box 6, Folder 8-20)
  - Dust jacket (Box 6, Folder 21)
- C. L. Sonnichsen, 1950-1991; 1970-1980
  This series contains the clippings, articles, reviews, and letters Roach used to craft her pamphlet on the life and work of C. L. Sonnichsen. Sonnichsen (1901-1991) was a noted folk historian who spent the major part of his life as a professor at the University of Texas at El Paso. He retired from UTEP in 1972 and became the director of publications at the Arizona Historical Society. Sonnichsen authored many books about the West including Cowboys & Cattle Kings, I'll Die Before I Run, Mescalero Apaches, and Pass of the North. The series includes many letters from Sonnichsen to Roach, some touching on personal matters and encouraging Roach in her writing efforts
  - Clippings re: Sonnichsen, 1950-1978 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1991 (Box 7, Folder 2-5)
  - Articles by Sonnichsen, 1961-1974 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Memoir of Henry and Mary Sonnichsen (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Autobiography (Box 7, Folder 8-9, Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Articles, clippings, notes (Box 8, Folder 2-7)
  - Audio tapes (Box 8, Folder 8-9)
  - Clippings (Box 8, Folder 10)